Okay, another discussion on an example.
And actually, it's one of the
examples from the last exercise week.
And of course, I won't discuss this in full
now here because that's the job of the exercise
videos that will also be made.
So, there will be a full discussion of
the example and alternatives, et cetera.
But there's one thing that I wanted to point
out already here now in the lecture, and that
is because it actually was a comment I made
towards the end of the last lecture week,
and that can be very nicely illustrated here.
So, let me recall this. There was this comment
about not shying away from using if-then-else
as a subexpression.
So, in the slides, I think it was one of the last
slides (in the current semester, slide 43) in the last week,
there was some comment
like: if you have something like, well, some
condition and if this condition is fulfilled,
then you apply some function to something;
else, we'll say expression one that was a
more complicated version on the slide, like
f x y (if exp1 then exp2 else exp3), let's say
we have something like if a condition holds,
then something which applies f to an expression.
And else, it so happens that we apply
the same function to another expression.
Okay, and then there was this comment in the
slides that actually does the equivalent,
I think it was written the
other way around in the slide.
But of course, it's an equation.
So, it doesn't matter which order.
I do this—this is the same semantically
as saying, let me apply f to something.
What is the something?
It's—well, if the condition is fulfilled, then
it's expression one, else it's expression two.
And I've noticed every time I give this lecture,
actually, that students somehow grappled with
this, right.
This is a valid transformation that can be
applied to Haskell code, but it's rarely done,
at least in the beginning.
And it has to do, I think, with the nature
of if-then-else, as an expression concept
in Haskell and like languages, compared to
completely different languages like imperative
languages, in which if-then-else is usually
understood as a command-level thing where
such nesting doesn't seem very
favorable or is not even possible.
Okay, well, it was an abstract comment, and
well, we did an action in your submissions.
This is not exactly.
I won't call out one specific student, but I
had a look at the submissions for the first
task of this week.
And typical solutions looked like this, of
course, with all the shape, but there are
versions like here, the 'scene' function. I
have two versions because they can be used
in two different ways.
So, if somehow the time parameter is smaller
than pi, then something is drawn, grass and
the rotated sun, and
otherwise, just grass is drawn.
It's, of course, organized here, that sun and
grass are actually given names and used as
reusable constructs, rather than
writing somehow complicated.
For example, this colored green rectangle
in these two places, so that there's grass,
grass instead of two times. This
expression is, of course, already nice.
But there's something else that can be improved
here, following this remark from above here,
which is one version when you
run it, and it solves the task.
So, there's nothing bad about this.
So, that's fine.
And here, the sun disappears.
And some other solutions among many versions
that can be done more and somehow, actually
letting the sun set at some place and then
leaving it there is also nice, basically
stopping this rotation
already, before we have made a half circle or
something like stopping at some point above
the horizon. Then there is this again and if-then-else,
so if some stop condition is not yet met,
we draw grass and the sun rotates to somewhere,
and otherwise, we also draw the grass and
the sun rotated to somewhere else,
namely to this stopping point, right?
And if you run this, then
we get a similar picture.
Well, it now looks—or similar animation that
now looks at the spinning. It looks the same,
and then it stops here because now the sun
after this 95% of the half circle, the sun
stops.
Okay, and these are fine solutions, but there's
something strange in some sense, or something
undesirable.
Namely, there's two times you have this
then-else and they both share something, right?
They both either draw grass and something
or just grass or grass and something,
or your grass and something else.
Okay, and now, duplication
is the enemy of programmers.
So, one might ask, wouldn't it be nicer to
not say if the condition holds, then we draw
grass and something else.
Otherwise, we draw grass and yet something
else.
Yeah, both in the "then" and "else"
branch, we have to draw the grass.
So, why do we even say this inside the
then-else if it's an unchanged part?
So, somehow the grass is not something which
differs between the "then" and the "else" branch,
so it shouldn't be necessary to
put it into the then-else parts.
Okay, and how can we actually do this?
But what can we do?
Well, that is exactly an instance
of this pattern here, right?
So, if some condition, right?
That's the condition here, then we do something
with some subexpression; else, we do the same
thing
but with another subexpression, and then the
recipe here says, well, let's express this
as we do the something.
So, that's what a function is, right?
It describes some computation, and
only the argument is conditional.
Okay, how does this fit in here?
Well, let's consider this operation of putting
the grass beside something else as a function
to let's say, this "grass
and …" is our function f.
What we have here is if some
condition, then "grass and".
And that's the changing subexpression.
Else, again, "grass and".
And this is a changing subexpression.
So, actually, we should have said this, or
could have said this as saying the scene
of t is "grass and",
so we will always draw grass, not just under some
conditions, and well, what is (after) the "and"?
What do we also have to draw?
Well, if t is smaller than this stopping
time, then we draw one kind of rotated sun,
and otherwise we draw the
other kind of rotated sun.
So, we move this common part of these two
expressions outside if-then-else because
this doesn't depend on the condition;
it doesn't even depend on the t, right?
So, previously, it looked like grass, depending
somehow on this condition, and maybe this
also on the t, but grass is a constant here.
So, it doesn't depend on a t.
Okay, so we avoid some duplication; of
course, not a big amount of duplication.
But in other expressions, it could be a larger
refactoring or more helpful refactoring, which
saves a lot of duplicated code.
And to express more clearly the scene always
contains grass, and then under some conditions,
different versions of the sun.
Okay, does this still work?
Well, of course it does, because
mathematically we have said exactly the same.
Because what I gave here and on a slide
last week is really a mathematical identity.
Yes, it does make perfect sense.
So, that's something that
motivates this moving out.
Okay, now we can ask ourselves there, was this
just because of this syntactic happenstance
that it looked exactly the same "grass and"
and we don't even have this here, right?
So, how can we move the grass
out of the scene1 function?
Yes, I just switched to scene1 here, which
of course still works and then the question
could be well, what now, so I can't move the
"grass and" outside of this thing, because it
doesn't occur in both the
"then" and the "else" branch.
Well, doesn't it? Let's consider again last
week, we had this nice concept of a neutral
element of some type and I talked about this
for lists but also for pictures. Actually,
pictures were the motivating example.
What is grass?
We want to see the else-branch as grass and
something, and the easy thing to do this is to say,
let's consider this grass as "grass and blank".
Yes, the blank picture is something that I
can always put beside my grass, for example.
And of course, the question is, would I do
this?
Right?
It looks stupid now, why did I complicate this
as branch from grass to "grass and blank"?
Well, on its own that would
probably indeed be a stupid change.
But now, I have actually rephrased my program
slightly in such a way that I can apply this
trick again, or this refactoring again, because
now I more clearly see that, really, the grass
is something which is common and even this
"grass and something" that is common to these
both branches, because I've made the nothing,
the two main blank picture explicit, but then
I can again pull this out, I can
say well, my scene1 is always grass.
Let's express this by having this here.
That's always grass and then conditioned on
this, I either have rotated the sun or simply
syntactically throwing away the "grass and" here,
otherwise, I have blank which also expresses
this nicely.
We always have the grass, under some conditions
I have rotated some sun, under other conditions
after some time, I have
nothing, maybe just the grass.
And again, this is more conceptually appealing
than the original version of this because I have
eliminated this duplicate grass occurrence
and I've made more conceptually clear what
is actually depending on the time,
namely, detect whether or not
I have a picture and if I have a picture of
that is-, that also clearly see under what
conditions I have nothing beside the grass.
Okay, and of course, it would still run.
Let's check this.
And it still works exactly the same way.
Okay, we have massaged the
program a bit using this hint.
Later in the future, maybe you do this
kind of refactoring on your own already.